Bavaria, August 1944
Come on!
All aboard!
- Get on the train, Lieutenant!
- Right away.
Come on! Come on!
Aboard!
All aboard!
Where were you?
The train's leaving.
I know.
I was at the doctor's.
Clemens, we're going
to have a baby.
Lisa.
Daddy, will you
send me a postcard?
I will.
Promise?
I promise.
A promise is a promise
that you never break.
No, I won't.
Last call, Lieutenant!
All aboard!
Come on!
I'll be back soon.
I promise.
I'll be back for Christmas!
As Far As My Feet Will Carry Me
Clemens Forell is hereby charged
with violating paragraphs 319 & 320.
The Court will now pronounce
judgment on him.
The defendant is guilty
of crimes against
the Partisans.
He is sentenced.
To 25 years of forced labor.
The sentence is in effect
starting today, 13 July 1945.
Forell!
It's your turn.
Everybody turn around!
He won't let go!
He wont' let go!
Hey, kid!
It's me!
He won't hurt you now.
He's dead.
Hello, Lisa.
I have something for you today.
Here...
And now I get a kiss.
What a little hussy!
Good day!
Lisa.
A letter from Clemens?
From the Red Cross:
We have no record of...
Clemens Forell in our lists.
There is no information about
the Russian court martial.
They know nothing.
Nothing!
Everything will
turn out all right.
Hail Mary...
Mother of mercy.
Please, bring my
father back home.
Daddy!
Hey, Danhorn.
You were at the
divisional headquarters.
And you made maps.
Yeah, and this is my reward.
Where's Cape Dezhnev?
Don't know much
about geography, huh?
Okay.
Here...
from north to south..
The Ural Mountains.
To the west...
That trivial place we can
now forget about: Europe.
The Irtysh River...
is behind us.
We much be here now.
Further east near
the Yenisey River.
The Lena...
The Vitim...
the little Olekma.
By the way,
here everything is little...
if it's shorter than
1,000 kilometers.
Cape Dezhnev...
Yes, well...
It's further east...
northeast.
It will take ages
to get there.
We'll never get there.
They'll let us starve and
freeze to death first.
Maybe we don't
deserve any better.
We did our duty.
You were in the SA.
And I'm proud of it!
Stop it!
Have you gone crazy?
- That's your last order, Captain!
- Hands off!
Four pieces each.
Less than usual.
Clemens, we're going
to have a baby!
I'll be back for Christmas!
I said four pieces, bastard!
Why do they get fed first?
You'll all get fed here!
Understand?
What about the
main course, Captain?
You won't have anything
to laugh about soon.
They're gonna let us die.
They uncoupled us,
so we'll die.
Mother, pray for me.
Don't let me die.
They're gonna let us die.
They're gonna shoot us.
They gotta shoot us.
Shut your fucking mouth!
Nothing to eat!
Come on, kid!
Pull yourself together!
My mother's last letter...
Gives me strength.
Hide it under your lapel.
Don't let them find it.
Try to sleep.
- What's going on?
- I don't know.
They've come for us.
They're taking us away.
Where to?
November,
somewhere in Siberia.
This letter will
never reach you.
It will never be sent.
I can't even write it.
I can hardly gather my thoughts
of what I want to say.
I saw that huge
screeching wheel.
That terrible thing which
crushes everything.
But I also realize that
no pain is irrevocable.
But constant hope is.
Cape Dezhnev Prison Camp, 1946
Headquarters
You saved the company.
You crossed the front line.
That's why you got a medal.
- You'll have a drink?
- No, thank you.
You could serve in the western
region or in Leningrad.
Instead, you are here in
Cape Dezhnev. Why?
Because I feel it's my duty.
The temptations of a woman!
Alright.
You are responsible
for camp security.
I hope you'll be
able to cope with it.
Thank you for your confidence, Major.
I'll do my best.
Barracks!
We made it!
Typhoid.
We can't go on like this.
We have penicillin. I know.
We got it from the Americans.
So, give it to me!
I'm warning you, Dr. Stauffer.
You're going to be responsible
if an epidemic breaks out!
Don't tell me what
I'm responsible for!
Don't forget who's
in charge here!
You're needed to
exam the prisoners.
We aren't finished, Lieutenant.
The Commander's orders.
And I'm here to carry them out.
- You're Dr. Stauffer?
- Yes, sir, Lieutenant!
You accompany Dr. Pachmutova.
There's a lot of work to do.
No fence!
No watchtowers!
They don't need things like
that north of the Arctic Circle.
Where would you go anyway?
No trees, no bushes
not even a blade
of grass to eat.
214, 215, 216.
A ship!
We're here at the eastern cape.
There must be a harbor around here.
Let's start again!
It's very tedious, Dr. Stauffer.
But there is one
great advantage.
This way we'll find out who's
healthy and fit for work.
- Then you don't need us.
- Yes, I do.
For the death certificates.
My letter.
Quiet!
What are you hiding?
Just a letter.
From my mother.
Take off all your clothes!
What are you doing?
Giving my coat
to my comrade.
What are you doing?
So he doesn't freeze to death.
May I say something, Lieutenant?
No.
What's your name?
Clemens Forell.
Keep your coat.
You'll need it.
Long live Stalin
Keep going, Forell.
What's wrong?
I gotta get out.
I can't take this anymore.
I can't stand it!
Go out and join Mattern!
And you'll get your fresh air!
What? Are these our
sleeping quarters?
- They'll be deloused.
We're supposed to
take everything off.
- I think this is mine.
- It's mine!
Let go!
The National Committe
of Free Germany.
Everyone who joins the right
side will get his chance.
- Forell, right?
- Clemens Forell.
- What's wrong?
- Daddy isn't dead.
No, Lisa.
I'm sure he isn't.
Sorry, nothing.
I don't have any information.
That doesn't mean he's dead.
New negotiations with the Russians
will take place this autumn.
You have to wait.
Wait.
Damn light!
Danhorn!
My God!
- Prisoner Forell!
- He's dead!
Comrade Lieutenant!
The engineer isn't here.
And that guy is too stupid.
Are you being treated well?
I'm not complaining, but...
Fine.
Come on.
Get the machine to work.
Me? How am I
supposed to do that?
You're a mechanic, prisoner Forell.
It's in your file.
You don't mean to
say it's wrong?
MS Alaska
Start it.
You speak Russian?
- That isn't mentioned in your file.
- Just a few words.
- Learn the right ones.
- Yeah.
Are you still alive,
prisoner Forell?
- Yes.
- Louder!
Yes, sir!
Lieutenant Kamenev!
That's fine! Where were you going?
Alaska?
The Union of the Soviet Republics...
...had an agreement with the
United States of North America.
Even if you'd managed to escape,
they'd have sent you back.
Attention!
That's fine.
You'll never leave this place.
You're going to
be buried here.
All of us.
Go on.
Your comrades
are waiting for you.
C'mon, Forell!
We're waiting for you!
Stop it!
You gotta stop it!
They really gave it to you.
I'm not surprised.
They're hungry.
Nothing to eat for five days.
Who's dump enough,
to run away...
the first chance he gets?
You'll never get
out that way.
Will he make it?
He's tough.
Take him to... sick bay.
That's an order.
He's running a high fever.
I hope it isn't typhoid.
Help me.
I have to...
I have to write home.
It will never arrive.
Hi there!
- Here, you must eat some good food.
- That's too much. Thank you.
Dear Dad, I want to
write you a letter,
but I don't know
where to send it.
Mom said that
you're in Russia.
But Russia is so big,
so far, so far away.
I'd really like
to see you again.
Do you know what this is?
These aren't spider webs,
like Pachmutova says.
There aren't any spiders here,
only lead.
- What do you mean?
- It causes lead poisoning.
Typesetters are advised
to find a new profession.
- And there's nothing
you can do? - No.
Everybody gets
it sooner or later.
I gotta go home.
Listen to me...
Forell.
- You could make it.
- But how?
You have to be prepared.
You need the right clothes,
sturdy shoes, a compass.
How will you find food?
What if you run into other people?
How do you start
a fire at 40 below?
- I know it's possible.
- Be quiet!
You don't know a thing.
If you reach the
Lena within a year,
you can kneel down
and thank God.
The Lena is in the
middle of Siberia.
Yeah.
I can help you.
- Reuter?
- Fit for work.
Baier?
Fit for work.
Klugmann?
I cleaned everything.
You see?
Everything's clean.
Spiders don't have a chance here.
Fit for work.
As soon as you get up.
Fever.
Penicillin.
- He's fit for work.
- No.
- I think so!
- He has a fever!
You don't decide,
Dr. Stauffer.
I'm responsible here.
I'm responsible for who gets
admitted and who gets released.
Fit for work.
Come see me tonight.
- Any problems?
- No. Okay.
Come here.
Danhorn drew this map
while he was still alive.
Of course,
it might not be precise.
A river that runs like this
can change its course.
The rivers are frozen in the winter but
they're like an ocean in the summer.
You'll have to wait
for the next winter...
Get in there!
Do you need me, Lieutenant?
You work too long, Dr. Stauffer.
- Why don't you... have a swig.
- Thanks.
Thank you.
It hits the spot.
Where did you get this?
Approved by
Command Headquarters.
I need it to cut splints
for fractured bones.
We're out of everything.
Don't work any
longer tonight.
- Turn off the light.
- Yeah.
- Good night.
We were lucky. There's no time left.
I can't tell you everything.
Come here.
My sweater. The boots.
Wear everything during the day.
Take some things off at night,
and loosely cover yourself with them.
Come on, let's get started.
- You have to show me just how...
- Do you want to escape? Yes or no?
- Of course I do!
- But only today! Now!
If you don't leave tonight, you'll go
back in the mine and never come out!
I've hidden supplies on the hill
where the train goes past.
Dried bread and lard
two kilos of machorka!
Don't smoke it.
You'll need it for trading.
A spirit cooker, a compass.
Snow shoes, too.
Where did you get all that?
It was actually
for my escape.
Here.
Carry it under you clothing.
Right next to your belly.
It's loaded.
Eight spare bullets.
They'll shoot you on the spot
if they find you with it.
Why don't you escape yourself?
There's a danger
of losing your voice.
Talk to yourself.
Talk to trees if you have to.
Take this along with you, too.
I scratched my address on it.
From my wife in Magdeburg.
Tell her I prepared everything
for my escape.
Yeah.
Why don't I escape?
Two months ago,
I stopped fooling myself.
Cancer.
I just have one request, Forell.
If you make it back,
go see my wife.
Tell her that I sent you,
and tell her...
...that I died in
the winter of '50.
February.
Describe the grave to her.
Tell her...
Tell her there's a
cross on my grave.
No, wait...
Tell her it was May.
She'll picture it with flowers.
That'll be more like spring.
Promise me?
Yeah, okay...
don't forget the map.
Here, take the knife with you.
I don't need it anymore.
You have a head start till tomorrow
morning. It's not enough.
They'll look for
you to the west.
Go north to the sea
and along the coast.
It's safer!
Come on, please.
I beg you.
- Excuse me.
- I beg you. Wait.
Please, allow me.
I'll take care of it.
You see, that's what
the German does.
He'll take care of it.
He's glad that
he can work.
And the two of us can...
I'm warning you.
I'm warning you! If you don't
stop flirting with the Germans,
- especially with that Forell...
- What?
What? Maybe you two
already have something going!
Stauffer!
Stand up when I talk to you!
Get up!
Get up, bastard!
Get to work!
Only if my men get something
decent to eat. Or we won't work.
You know who's to blame.
You're blaming us, too.
That isn't fair.
You talk about fairness!
Yes.
You can kill us all but we will never
beat one of our comrades again.
Lieutenant, the search
patrol reports back.
What do you
have to report?
We combed the
plains to the west.
All the way to the foothills.
He couldn't have
gone that far.
We've been gone for five days.
We're completely exhausted.
I believe he's buried
under the snow.
You are expected to
carry out orders!
You failed to do the job!
Go on!
You've lost control
over the camp.
You didn't fulfill your duty.
One of them escaped.
You shot one.
That is sabotage.
He put up resistance.
Okay, let's assume
that's right.
And Forell may have
frozen to death.
Write that in your report.
No... he isn't dead.
Our Father...
who art in Heaven...
Give us our daily bread...
My bread,
give me it now!
Give me it now!
I'm sorry, but I need your fat.
I have to go home.
997, 998, 999...
3,000.
001, 002,
003, 004...
You're...
you're a tree! A tree!
You're a tree!
I'm gonna make it!
I'm gonna make it.
Have all stations
been informed?
Yes, within a radius
of 500 kilometers.
Increase the radius.
He can go further than 500
kilometers in two months.
Drop your guns!
It's all right.
We don't want
anything from you.
We easily could have
shot you already.
But we're hunters
and gold-diggers.
In the summer,
we wash gold.
And in the winter, we hunt.
We saw the fire.
And we thought
we'd take a look.
You must be German.
And you ran away?
It will be light soon.
A snowstorm is approaching.
You must look for
a safe place.
We know a safe place.
Come on. Let's go.
I don't need you two.
Go away.
Go away!
Whatever you say.
Let's go!
Anastas!
What's taking you?
So, you still don't believe us?
I'm Semyon.
What's your name?
Pjotr.
Right.
Don't trust anybody.
And never tell anyone
your real name.
Come with us.
You'll never make
it alone in Siberia.
It's becoming spring, Lisa.
I'm on my way to you.
Should I thank God for that,
or my Siberian companions?
It's just a small piece of
the way I have to go.
Semyon said it was
10,000 verst,
and then he laughed.
Semyon is always laughing.
When will we reach
the Kalyma Mountains?
In two days, maybe in three.
But the river flows north.
No, 500 kilometers
to the west.
Take me home, Anastas...
On this raft.
We're crossing the Caucasians.
You'll make it.
If anybody can, he can.
It would be possible.
But actually you
shouldn't leave.
Look around you.
How magnificent.
Siberia is!
Fertile and beautiful.
You can be very
happy here.
Okay, Pjotr.
You take the oar.
Now show us what
you've learned.
Stay to the left!
Anastas!
Straight ahead!
Ana...
Ana... Anastas...
Anastas would have
let me drown.
Thank you, Petja.
Eat, Pjotr.
Eat.
You can eat these leaves.
I'll teach you everything.
Why did you take
me with you?
We ran away from
the goldmines.
Anastas thought that
you might give us away.
Sooner or later they'd
have caught you anyway.
- But now you're one of us.
- No!
No, I didn't drown!
What should I have done?
Deserted the raft with all our supplies?
- Where's my pack?
- It's gone. It sank.
Hey, it's all here!
What happened to my things?
I thought maybe
you had some salt.
We haven't had salt
for a long time.
What do you need
that for anyway?
There are cities and streets here
that you've never heard of before.
The rivers are
being re-routed.
Everywhere they're building,
researching and collectivizing.
That's how it is in the
Soviet Union today.
Do you have any
salt perhaps?
Didn't you check... to see?
What an idiot I am!
Salt!
Vodka!
What luck, Petruchka!
Why did you kill him?
Why do you think?
We have to bury him.
He'll be taken care of
now by the wolves.
He wanted to
steal my gold.
Listen, Petja.
Take your things and let's go.
We'll get by without him.
Come on.
I'm heading home,
step by step.
Even if I have to go
roundabout ways.
This is what I've learned:
The southern route to the west,
goes north sometimes,
towards the east.
I'm done with.
I can't go on.
We'll make it, Semyon.
We have to go on.
Give me your pack. I'll carry it.
That's very nice of you.
But there's only enough
gold for one of us!
For one of us!
Lisa.
It was just a dream.
Just a dream.
Clam down, sweetheart.
I'm thirsty.
- I'll get you something.
- Okay.
Okay!
You're talking like a Yankee.
- You dreamed about
Daddy again. - Yes.
It's me, Kolka!
And that's...
Alyoshka!
Prisoner of war...
You talked in your sleep.
This is Irina.
Her grandfather healed you.
He heals everyone who is ill.
But he couldn't
help her husband.
The bears tore him apart.
My wife.
My son.
I have to go away.
For a long time,
with the dogs.
But don't be afraid.
No one will harm you here.
But you must
drink and eat,
so you get your
strength back.
- Okay?
- Yes...
I am Clemens.
This is all we
know about him.
The keys.
He wanted to buy a passport
with the gold he stole.
- Imagine that, Comrade Kamenev.
- I'm not interested in him.
I need the other man mentioned
in the report, a German.
- Did he talk about the German?
- Yes, sir, Comrade Kamenev.
Ask him yourself if that's
the German you're looking for.
Attention! State Security asks all
residents of Yakutsk for their help.
Be on the lookout for a
German spy named Pjotr.
His real name is Clemens Forell.
Forell, I have a son!
He's my son! Mine!
What a great little guy!
Look how big he is!
He's going to be a real giant!
Do you have a son?
I don't know.
- I hope so. - You'll find out.
I'm sure you'll find out.
They're looking for you.
It's too dangerous for you.
I have to go away.
Aljoshka will take you
to the great forests.
And then...
you'll be on your own.
Thank you for everything.
Argish!
He likes you and
will go with you.
He's a good hunting dog,
and a small bone is all he needs.
- Alright... good luck.
- Thank you.
Ringing cedar.
It will protect you.
The spirit of the
shaman is with you.
Go home and...
forget my name.
Go now!
Go!
Argish,
go and look after him.
Summer 1951
Hey there!
Don't move!
Come here!
Move it!
- What's your name?
- Answer the Comrade Inspector!
Pjotr Ivanovich.
I'm from the Baltic.
My 8 years of forced
labor are over.
I have to report to the Rayon
commander of the MWD...
in...
...in Chita.
Here.
Chita.
You have a permit?
No, I don't.
- But... An I.D.?
- Yes...
But it's being sent by courier.
Otherwise I could escape.
With an I.D.
I know all about
you bastards.
You know how
far it is to Chita?
Far.
Very far.
800 kilometers.
- Damn dog!
- He's hungry.
We didn't find much
to eat in the forest.
Got out & have them
give you some food.
Thank you,
Comrade Inspector.
We have to report him.
We will, but first we have
to send off our freight.
You're lucky!
There's a freight
train going to Chita.
You're going along
as the brakeman.
Make sure no tramps
hitch a ride.
You check the chains.
- You understand?
- Yeah.
Let's go!
- Bye!
- Good luck.
Attention!
Comrade Lieutenant the
unit is ready for action!
Commanding officer,
Lieutenant Zykov.
- How many men?
- Fifteen.
- Button up your jacket.
- Sorry.
Hey, come on.
We're here.
We gotta go!
He isn't here!
At the front of the train!
Be quiet!
Almost on time, Prisoner Forell.
Argish!
Stop it!
It is walled within the ground,
then formed and fired from clay.
Hurry, come around, craftsmen,
the ball must be finished today.
It is walled within the ground,
then formed and fired from clay.
Craftsmen, hurry, come around,
the bell must be finished today.
Learn as much as you can.
Keep on learning.
The Wanderer's Night Song
Hush'd on the hill the breeze; Scarce by
the zephyr the trees softly are pressed
The woodbird's asleep on the bough.
Wait then, and thou.
Soon will find rest.
That was very nice.
Elisabeth.
Go to your seat.
Who else has memorized a poem?
Rudolf.
Central Asian U.S.S.R.,
August 1952
Lord, forgive my sins...
Forgive me.
Wonders will never cease!
A German asks...
...for forgiveness.
You're obvious.
There are lots of
poor destitutes here,
but I've never seen a German
destitute here before.
If you pardon
the expression,
you have quite
a strong odor.
You can freshen
up at my home.
I want to help you.
Is it a long way?
You have trouble walking?
It's better to take
the side streets.
Soviet Police Headquarters
Come with me.
My brothers...
We came from Poland.
I went to the Soviet Union
and they went to Gdansk.
An uncle of ours lived there.
I burned it...
...when I received the
news that... that also...
Take sugar.
Were you in a camp?
Why did you burn the photograph
of your brothers?
Because I can't look
them in the eyes.
I'm sorry.
That's easily said.
What shall we do
with you now?
You need a passport.
- A passport? - You can't
cross the border otherwise.
Do you have a name that
you've chosen for yourself?
- Pjotr.
Pjotr Ivanovich Ulyanov.
That's about as common here
as Hans Peter Muller in Germany.
Why are you doing
this for me?
You want to know why a
Jew would help a German?
Although you Germans
killed my brothers.
Not all of us knew about it.
Of course not.
You'd have fought to
save women and children.
You'd have killed your
commanding officer instead.
But you didn't know a thing.
They kept it a secret.
You only did your duty.
I'm doing my duty, too.
We'll prepare a bath
for you now.
I feel a bit queasy.
At least the haircut fits.
Wait here.
It could take a few hours.
When I leave,
I turn off the lights.
Stay here in the dark.
- Try to sleep.
- Alright.
No confidence?
I've learned to be careful.
You have to learn to
trust people again.
Your passport
and travel permit.
The trip costs nothing.
A Soviet achievement.
Now listen,
Pjotr Ivanovich Ulyanov.
You're Latvian.
That explains your accent.
Memorize the information.
You have to hurry now.
The meeting place is at
the end of the street.
Why are you
doing this for me?
Do you have a
bad conscience,
because you didn't
help a Jew?
You'll have to sort
that out yourself.
Go now. With a little luck,
you'll make it.
Thank you.
What's wrong?
I've heard of
your hospitality.
May I come in?
Daddy, will you
send me a postcard?
This postcard, please.
20 copecks.
We have our suspicions
about you.
But no evidence.
But who needs evidence!
You don't think that
I'd help a German.
I just have to know
where he is.
Understand?
Yes, I helped him.
And I'd to it again.
I'd help anyone.
Understand?
There's been a landslide.
You'll have to
make a detour.
That'll take us
out of our way.
What can I do?
Is it possible to walk there?
Yes, but it's very far.
How did you get here?
There was a landslide
in the mountains.
That's why I walked.
You walked?
It's very far.
Yes.
You see... I have to cross
the border today.
Here...
valid on 13 August.
The Iranians probably won't
let me cross tomorrow.
Yes, the Iranians probably
won't let you in.
You can go across.
Thanks.
Glory to the Red Army
it's my victory.
Teheran Federal Prison,
December 1952
We believe that
he's a Russian spy.
He'll be sentenced to death.
He calls himself
Clemens Forell and says
he escaped from Siberia's
eastern shore.
He says it took him
3 years to get here.
It sounds so incredible
that it might even be true.
That is why I granted
his request
and asked you to
come and identify him.
The last time I saw him...
...was 1937.
Before I was appointed to the
Ministry of Economics in Ankara.
We shall find out if he
really is my nephew.
You have my complete support,
Mr. Baudrexel.
Uncle.
Don't you recognize me?
- You claim to be my nephew.
- It's me.
Sit down.
If you're Clemens Forell...
I'd like you to answer
some questions.
Mountain Troop
Regiment Reichenhall.
I gave my mother the photograph
for her birthday in '39.
I wrote it on the back.
To my dear mother
on her birthday.
15 July, 1939...
Clemens.
Put the hat!